Guide to the Trinidad Rojo Papers
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Trinidad Rojo papers
1923-1994
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
3586
Rojo, Trinidad
6.19 cubic feet 12 boxes
University of Washington student, President of International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, author, sociologist
Filipino author, sociologist, labor union official. Rojo was a president of ILWU No. 7. He was a student at the University of Washington and at Stanford, where he was a research fellow.
Arranged into 7 accessions:
Accession no. 3586-001, Trinidad Rojo papers, before 1984
Accession no. 3586-002, Trinidad Rojo papers, 1932-1988
Accession no. 3586-003, Trinidad Rojo papers, 1956-1966
Accession no. 3586-004, Trinidad Rojo papers, 1923-1991
Accession no. 3586-005, Trinidad Rojo papers, 1937-1985
Accession no. 3586-006, Trinidad Rojo papers, 1932-1991
Accession no. 3586-007, Trinidad Rojo papers, 1929-1994
Consult the scope and content information for each of the accessions listed below.
Consult the access restrictions information for each of the accessions listed below.
Rojo, Trinidad$vArchives; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Cannery Workers and Farm Laborers Union. Local 7 (Seattle, Wash.); Filipino Alumni Association (University of Washington); International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union; International Longshoremen's And Warehousemen's Union.$bLocal 37; Philippines; Labor Unions$xOfficials and employees
Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor History; Labor Unions; Washington (State); Seattle
- Trinidad Rojo papers, before 1984; 3586-001; 1.00 cubic foot 1 box
  Plays and articles relating to the politics of the Philippine Islands and the ILWU, Local 37.
  Open to all users.
  Deposited by Trinidad Rojo, 6/1/1983.
  - SERIES I: WRITINGS, 1932-circa 1989 (Box-folder 1/1-1/18)
    - Far East Landgrabbing (First Draft) PREFACE By Trinidad A. Rojo, 1939-1942 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Filipino-American Struggle From Submergence to Emergence By Trinidad A Rojo (Part 1 of 2), 1937-1971 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Filipino-American Struggle From Submergence to Emergence By Trinidad A Rojo (Part 2 of 2), 1937-1971 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Far East Landgrabbing PART II By Trinidad A. Rojo (Part 1 of 2), 1934-1941 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Far East Landgrabbing PART II By Trinidad A. Rojo (Part 2 of 2), 1934-1941 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Far East Landgrabbing PART I By Trinidad A Rojo, 1940-1941 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Memorial Rizal Amerasian University Education for World Peace By Trinidad A. Rojo, circa 1959-circa 1989 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Far East Landgrabbing By Trinidad A. Rojo, circa 1982 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Roots of Red Rebellion By Trinidad A. Rojo, circa 1960s (Box-folder 1/9)
    - A Critique of the Energy Program for the Philippines By Trinidad A. Rojo, 1980 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Subjects for Lectures By Trinidad A. Rojo, 1957 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - ILWU, Local 37 (formerly Local 7) Rojo Presidency Campaign Materials and 1940 Local 7 Foreman-Delegate Rules, 1940-1953 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Poems by Trinidad A. Rojo, circa 1960s (Box-folder 1/13)
    - Trinidad A. Rojo Biographical Information, 1965-1982 (Box-folder 1/14)
    - Application for a Planning Grant for the Establishment of the Office of the Malayo-Polynesian-Amerasian Coordinators, and an International Southeast Asian-American Research, Cultural Institute, Under the Office of the Mayor of Seattle, Washington, Wes Uhl, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 1/15)
    - Letter to Mrs. Cleve Scott By Trinidad A. Rojo and Various Writings by Kathleen R. Doss, 1971-1983 (Box-folder 1/16)
    - Letter to Dr. Hugh Hotson, President, Maritime Building Corporation By Trinidad A. Rojo, 1945-1983 (Box-folder 1/17)
    - Assorted Creative, Academic and Professional Writings by Trinidad A. Rojo, 1932-1982 (Box-folder 1/18)
- Trinidad Rojo papers, 1932-1988; 3586-002; .42 cubic foot 1 box
  Biographical features, correspondence, bibliography of Rojo's works, writings, plays, poems, and song lyrics.
  Donated by Trinada Rojo, 7/22/1988.
  - SERIES I: WRITINGS, 1931-1992 (Box-folder 1/1-1/10)
    - Site Analysis & Development Master Plan: Dr. Jose Rizal Park, 1975 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Rojo Poems: Comparative Analysis & Introductions, Undated (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Rizal Week, Rojo Poetry, & WA Commission for the Humanities, 1973-1986 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Rojo & Filipinos: Essays, Transcripts, Playwrites & Music, 1932-1989 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Local 37, Local 7; Rojo Review, Poetry & Awards, 1988 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Note of Return: Filipino-American-Japanese Relations, Rojo Typescript, 1947, 1992 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Capt. Magsaysay & the Huks Playwrite, 1947 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Bataan University Broadcasts & Filipino-American Relations Essay & Outline, 1946-1987 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Local 37 Birth & Growth, Local 7, & Cultural Arts Analysis, 1952-1987 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - "My Five Years in America" by David P. De Tagle (Spanish), 1931 (Box-folder 1/10)
- Trinidad Rojo papers, 1956-1986; 3586-003; .42 cubic foot 1 box
  Primarily writings, some correspondence.
  Donated by Trinidad Rojo, 12/11/1990.
  - SERIES I: WRITINGS, 1937-1991 (Box-folder 1/1-1/11)
    - Trinidad Rojo's Memorandum to Miss Karyl Winn, Chief Archivist of the UW Libraries, 1938-1991 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Epistolary Fiction by Ildefonso Redadtrini, Undated (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Biographical Information Written about Trinidad A. Rojo, 1939-1987 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Letters and a Resolution Regarding Jose Rizal Commemorations, 1960-1982 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Southeast Asian-American Cultural Center By Trinidad A. Rojo, 1972 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Touristic, Commercial, Industrial and Cultural Centers Part One By Trinidad A. Rojo, circa 1970s (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Memorial Rizal Amerasian University Education for World Peace by Trinidad A. Rojo, 1945 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Assorted Non-Fiction Writing by Trinidad A Rojo, 1937-circa 1960 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Southeast Asian Regionalism and Stable Peace: Volume One By Trinidad A. Rojo (1 of 2), 1966-1972 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Southeast Asian Regionalism and Stable Peace: Volume One By Trinidad A. Rojo (2 of 2), 1966-1972 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Records and Proceedings of the Third Filipino Inter-Community Conference, 1941 (Box-folder 1/11)
- Trinidad Rojo papers, 1923-1991; 3586-004; .83 cubic foot 2 boxes
  Writings, report, correspondence, testimony, sheet music with lyrics by Rojo.
  Donated by Trinidad Rojo, 1/1/1991.
  - SERIES I: WRITINGS, 1940-1992 (Box-folder 1/1-1/12)
    - Bio- and Autobiographical Information and Images of Trinidad Rojo, 1956-1986 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Nonfiction Writing by Trinidad A. Rojo (Part 1 of 2), 1956-1985 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Nonfiction Writing by Trinidad A. Rojo (Part 2 of 2), 1956-1985 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Poetry, Lyrics and Fiction by Trinidad A. Rojo, circa 1980 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Pan Amerasian Company Papers, 1968-1991 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Local 7 Union Papers, 1940-1981 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Constitution and By-laws: Garolijo Transoceanic Developers Co., 1984 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Labor-Related Nonfiction Writing by Trinidad A. Rojo, 1944-circa 1947 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Jose Rizal Commemoration and Research, 1973-1980 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - University of Washington Filipino Alumni Association, 1972-1986 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Trinidad A. Rojo Correspondence, 1940-1992 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Assorted Papers, 1944-1989 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - SERIES II: REPORTS, 1937-1971 (Box-folder 2/1-2/8)
    - Report to the Second International Convention of the United Cannery, Agricultural, Packing and Allied Workers of America, 1938 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Letter and Transcription of National Radio Broadcasting Company's Broadcast for Bataan University, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Records and Minutes of the Meetings of Stockholders and Directors of Air-Walls, Inc. (Part 1 of 2), 1948-1957 (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Records and Minutes of the Meetings of Stockholders and Directors of Air-Walls, Inc. (Part 2 of 2), 1948-1957 (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Immigration and Population Problems By Trinidad A. Rojo, circa 1944 (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Southeast Asian Regionalism and Stable Peace By Trinidad A. Rojo (Part 1 of 2), 1937-1971 (Box-folder 2/6)
    - Southeast Asian Regionalism and Stable Peace By Trinidad A. Rojo (Part 2 of 2), 1937-1971 (Box-folder 2/7)
    - Filipino-American-Japanese Relations By Trinidad A. Rojo, 1947 (Box-folder 2/8)
- Trinidad Rojo papers, 1937-1985; 3586-005; .21 cubic foot 1 box
  Prose writings, one poem, play "Far East Land Grabbing", photograph, photocopied clippings.
  Donated by Trinidad Rojo, 8/30/1993.
  - SERIES I: WRITINGS, 1937-1987 (Box-folder 1/1-1/7)
    - The Language Problem in the Philippines By Trinidad A. Rojo, 1937 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Report to the Consumer Department of the State Attorney's Office on Gumboc Illegal Duplex and Cris-Crossed Electrical Wiring by Trinidad A. Rojo, 1974-1985 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Photograph and Photocopied Images of Trinidad A. Rojo and a Press Release on Hydrogen Fuel by Cesar Escosa, 1940-1987 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Letter from United Cannery, Agricultural, Packing and Allied Workers of America General President to Trinidad A. Rojo, 1940 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Southeast Asian Regionalist Anthem Lyrics: Youths of Our Greater Fatherland, Undated (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Unregulated, Destructive Nationalism and the Road to Lasting Peace By Trinidad A. Rojo, 1945 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Far East Landgrabbing By Trinidad A. Rojo, circa 1940 (Box-folder 1/7)
- Trinidad Rojo papers, 1932-1991; 3586-006; .21 cubic foot 1 box
  Writings, ephemera.
  Donated by Trinidad Rojo, 6/13/1994.
  - SERIES I: WRITINGS, 1939,1952 (Box-folder 1/1-1/2)
    - Rojo 1952 ILWU Local 37 Presidency Pamphlet (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Excerpts on Alaska Congressional Fisheries Hearings with Special Reference to the Salmon Cannery Industry, Traps, Non-Resident Workers, Whites, Filipinos, Others, Etc., 1939 (Box-folder 1/2)
- Trinidad Rojo papers, 1929-1994; 3586-007; 3.1 cubic feet 5 boxes
  Unpublished manuscripts of scholarship on labor and living conditions of Filipino American cannery workers and scholarship, poems, and articles related to various other aspects of the community and its history. Newspapers from the Phillipines and Filipino American community newspapers from Seattle, San Francisco, Los Angeles and Stockton.
  View selections from this collection in digital format.
  Use restricted until processed.
  Donor: Celso Tolman, November 17, 2012.
  - SERIES I: CANNERY WORKERS UNION RECORDS, 1940-1944 (Box-folder 1/1-1/3)
    - Local 7- UCAPAWA- CIO Annual Report, 1944 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Cannery Workers Union, 1940 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Cannery Union Annual Budget, 1944 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - SERIES II: TRINIDAD ROJO PERSONAL PAPERS, 1926-1995 (Box-folder 1/4-5/1)
    - Subseries A: Manuscripts, 1926, 1940-1982 (Box-folder 1/4-2/14)
      - "Taruc's Kangaroo Court", 1944-1946 (Box-folder 1/4)
      - Script, 1957 (Box-folder 1/5)
      - Memo by Trinidad A. Rojo, 1982 (Box-folder 1/6)
      - "Vestiges of the Last Glacial Age", "From Duel to Ambush", Undated (Box-folder 1/7)
      - Manuscript, Undated (Box-folder 1/8)
      - Manuscript, "A Nightmare", Undated (Box-folder 1/9)
      - Summary, Undated (Box-folder 1/10)
      - Manuscript, 1950 (Box-folder 1/11)
      - Appendices, Undated (Box-folder 1/12)
      - "Prologue: Tripumphant Death, Imerialism and Colonialism", Undated (Box-folder 1/13)
      - "U. S. Asian-American Problems", Undated (Box-folder 1/14)
      - Chapter 14, notes, correspondence, 1963 (Box-folder 1/15)
      - Manuscript, Undated (Box-folder 1/16)
      - References, Undated (Box-folder 1/17)
      - Cultural Arts and Applied Arts, Undated (Box-folder 1/18)
      - Micellaneous mail and essay, Undated (Box-folder 1/19)
      - Handwritten notes and clippings, Undated (Box-folder 1/20)
      - Philippines, 1940 (Box-folder 1/21)
      - Filipino-American Report, Undated (Box-folder 2/1)
      - Manuscript, Undated (Box-folder 2/2)
      - "Man, the Super Crocodile", Undated (Box-folder 2/3)
      - Manuscripts, 1926-1936 (Box-folder 2/4)
      - "Magsaysay's Answer to the Reds", Undated (Box-folder 2/5)
      - Manuscripts, Undated (Box-folder 2/6)
      - Chapter 13, manuscript, Undated (Box-folder 2/7)
      - Chapter 5, manuscript, Undated (Box-folder 2/8)
      - Chapter 9, manuscript, Undated (Box-folder 2/9)
      - Memo to Mr. Uldarico Mosquito, 1978 (Box-folder 2/10)
      - Manuscripts, Undated (Box-folder 2/11)
      - Manuscript, Undated (Box-folder 2/12)
      - Memorandum, Undated (Box-folder 2/13)
      - Manuscript, Undated (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Subseries B: Correspondence, 1938-1995 (Box-folder 2/15-3/9)
    - Correspondence, arbitration booklet, 1945-1974 (Box-folder 2/15)
    - Correspondence, 1938-1995 (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Correspondence, 1985 (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Personal notes, correspondence, Undated (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Correspondence, 1938-1942 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Correspondence, 1961 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1991 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Correspondence, 1939 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Correspondence, 1948 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Correspondence, 1948 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Subseries C: Subject Files, 1938-1994 (Box-folder 3/10-4/1)
    - Photographs, Death certificate, 1994 (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Social Security Administration, 1986-1990 (Box-folder 3/11)
    - Articles of Incorporation, 1973 (Box-folder 3/12)
    - Pan Amerasian Company letterhead, Undated (Box-folder 3/13)
    - Advertisements, Undated (Box-folder 3/14)
    - Death Certificate, 1994 (Box-folder 3/15)
    - Housing Records, 1990-1993 (Box-folder 3/16)
    - Personal files, Undated (Box-folder 3/17)
    - Personal File, Undated (Box-folder 3/18)
    - Pan Amerasian Company, 1938-1990 (Box-folder 3/19)
    - Contracts: Kathleen Doss, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 3/20)
    - Housing Records, 1974-1991 (Box-folder 3/21)
    - Financial Records, 1948 (Box-folder 3/22)
    - Filipino Community of Seattle, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 3/23)
    - University of Washington: Silvano Tallido, 1934-1937 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Subseries D: Press Clippings, 1930-1992 (Box-folder 4/2-5/1)
    - New Republic: Germany as the Moscow Conference Opens, 1947 (Box-folder 4/2)
    - Press, financial records, 1933-1992 (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Press: Philippines, 1930 (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Press, 1947-1970 (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Caballeros De Dimas-Alang Press, 1933-1937 (Box-folder 4/6)
    - Press Clippings, 1937-1939 (Box-folder 4/7)
    - Atlas of Philippine Statistics, 1939 (Box-folder 4/8)
    - Press Clippings, Undated (Box-folder 5/1)